window.__examLoadCallback({
  "title": "Data_Structure - Heap_Tree — Slot 1 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Heap_Tree — Slot 1",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>A meld operation on two instances of a data structure combines them into one single instance of the same data structure. Consider the following data structures:  <br><br>\nP: Unsorted doubly linked list with pointers to the head node and tail node of the list.<br>\nQ: Min-heap implemented using an array.<br>\nR: Binary Search Tree.<br><br>\nWhich ONE of the following options gives the worst-case time complexities for meld operation on instances of size \\(n \\) of these data structures? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>P: \\(\\Theta(1) \\),  Q: \\(\\Theta(n) \\),  R: \\(\\Theta(n) \\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>P: \\(\\Theta(1) \\),  Q: \\(\\Theta(n \\log n) \\),  R: \\(\\Theta(n) \\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>P: \\(\\Theta(n) \\),  Q: \\(\\Theta(n \\log n) \\),  R: \\(\\Theta(n^2) \\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>P: \\(\\Theta(1) \\),  Q: \\(\\Theta(n) \\),  R: \\(\\Theta(n \\log n) \\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>P: \\(\\Theta(1) \\),  Q: \\(\\Theta(n) \\),  R: \\(\\Theta(n) \\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460807/gate-cse-2025-set-2-question-28#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>The height of any rooted tree is defined as the maximum number of edges in the path from the root node to any leaf node. Suppose a Min-Heap \\(T\\) stores 32 keys. The height of \\(T\\) is _____________. (Answer in integer) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "5",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460055/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-25#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Consider a binary min-heap containing 105 distinct elements. Let \\(k\\)  be the index (in the underlying array) of the maximum element stored in the heap. The number of possible values of \\(k\\) is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>53</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>52</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>27</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>1</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>53</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422809/gate-cse-2024-set-1-question-33#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>An array \\([82,101,90,11,111,75,33,131,44,93] \\) is heapified. Which one of the following options represents the first three elements in the heapified array? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(82,90,101 \\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(82,11,93 \\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(131,11,93 \\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(131,111,90 \\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(131,111,90 \\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422811/gate-cse-2024-set-1-question-31#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Let A be a priority queue for maintaining a set of elements. Suppose A is\nimplemented using a max-heap data structure. The operation Extract-Max(A)\nextracts and deletes the maximum element from A. The operation Insert(A,key)\ninserts a new element key in A. The properties of a max-heap are preserved at the\nend of each of these operations.<br>\nWhen A contains n elements, which one of the following statements about the worst\ncase running time of these two operations is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2023)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Both Extract-Max(A) and Insert(A,key) run in O(1).</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Both Extract-Max(A) and Insert(A,key) run in O(log(n)).</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Extract-Max(A) runs in O(1) whereas Insert(A,key) runs in O(n).</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Extract-Max(A) runs in O(1) whereas Insert(A,key) runs in O(log(n)).</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Both Extract-Max(A) and Insert(A,key) run in O(log(n)).</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/399275/gate-cse-2023-question-36#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following sequences when stored in an array at locations\nA[1], . . . , A[10] forms a max-heap? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2023)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>23, 17, 10, 6, 13, 14, 1, 5, 7, 12</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>23, 17, 14, 7, 13, 10, 1, 5, 6, 12</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>23, 17, 14, 6, 13, 10, 1, 5, 7, 15</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>23, 14, 17, 1, 10, 13, 16, 12, 7, 5</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>23, 17, 14, 7, 13, 10, 1, 5, 6, 12</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/399310/gate-cse-2023-question-2#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>Let H be a binary min-heap consisting of n elements implemented as an array. What is the worst case time complexity of an optimal algorithm to find the maximum element in H? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (1)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (\\log n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta ( n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (n \\log n)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta ( n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357538/gate-cse-2021-set-2-question-2#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Consider the array representation of a binary min-heap containing 1023 elements. The minimum number of comparisons required to find the maximum in the heap is ___________. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "511",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333184/gate2020-cs-47#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following statements:<br><br>\nI. The smallest element in a max-heap is always at a leaf node.<br>\nII. The second largest element in a max-heap is always a child of the root node.<br>\nIII. A max-heap can be constructed from a binary search tree in \\(\\Theta (n)\\) time.<br>\nIV. A binary search tree can be constructed from a max-heap in \\(\\Theta (n)\\) time.<br><br>\nWhich of the above statements is/are TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2019)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>I, II and III</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>I, II and IV</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>I, III and IV</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>II, III and IV</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>I, II and III</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/302808/gate2019-cs-40#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Given a binary-max heap. The elements are stored in an arrays as 25,14,16,13,10,8,12. What is the content of the array after two delete operations? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>14,13,8,12,10</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>14,12,13,10,8</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>14,13,12,8,10</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>14,13,12,10,8</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>14,13,12,8,10</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/213531/isro2018-57\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>The number of possible min-heaps containing each value from {1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7} exactly once is _____. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "80",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/204121/gate2018-46#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>A complete binary min-heap is made by including each integer in [1,1023] exactly once. The depth of a node in the heap is the length of the path from the root of the heap to that node. Thus, the root is at depth 0. The maximum depth at which integer 9 can appear is_____.\n. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "8",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39585/gate2016-2-34#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>An operator delete(i) for a binary heap data structure is to be designed to delete the item in the i-th node.Assume that the heap is implemented in an array and i refers to the i-th index of thearray.If the heap tree has depth d (number of edges on the path from the root to the farthest leaf),the n what is the time complexity to re-fix the heap efficiently after the removal of the element? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2016 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>O(1)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>O(d) but not O(1)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>O(\\(2^{d}\\)) but not O(d)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>O(d \\(2^{d}\\)) but not O(\\(2^{d}\\))</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>O(d) but not O(1)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/39706/gate2016-1-37#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following array of elements. <br>\n(89,19,50,17,12,15,2,5,7,11,6,9,100) <br>The minimum number of interchanges needed to convert it into a max-heap is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>4</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>5</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>2</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>3</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>3</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8418/gate2015-3-20#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Consider a complete binary tree where the left and the right subtrees of the root are max-heaps. The lower bound for the number of operations to convert the tree to a heap is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2015 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Omega (log n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\((n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Omega (n \\; log n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Omega (n^{2})\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Omega (log n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/8091/gate2015-2-12#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
});
